welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
in sensing the new myth we're going to
be speaking with artists storytellers
musicians and mythologists that are
committing themselves to sensing the
emergent art and myth and culture rather
than maybe clinging on to a dominant
narrative or story allowing themselves
to be stewards of what is a more
beautiful world what are more beautiful
stories and how do we live them and I've
been inspired by Peters reflections that
beauty is found in communitas and they
here at the stoah with my fellow
comrades and sense makers and artists
and experience designers we are
endeavoring to seduce the culture as
Peter puts it into creating a more
beautiful culture to living a beautiful
story and that's what really what I am
feeling inspired by in my experiences
here with you all is developing
community for the long haul like I want
to like these some of these connections
and relationships that I'm making I
really want to be committed to the long
game of our relationship and what is
that we're creating together and
experiencing a more rich mythology so
that's why I called the series sensing
the new myth as I am wanting to sense
into what is an artful expression that
wants to happen through me that will
beautify the world around me and so
Andrew I'd love to hear from you some of
the thoughts at the edge of your
thinking like what is beauty really
and how are have you been reinventing it
for yourself lately okay well first of
all thank you very much for inviting me
Tyson and thank you I think it was
Timothy you said beauty is the your
compass or your core and I think that's
that's just absolutely perfect that's
absolutely I feel the same way I feel
that beauty is the compass and the core
not just my compass in the core but the
compass in the core so I think that's
exactly right and I also agree with was
it Jordan who said that you know we're
no longer up to the task like the
culture is falling apart
and this is why there's so much ugliness
so I'm just gonna ramble here a little
bit about you know my thoughts on beauty
and also the denial of beauty and I'm
gonna start with that because I don't
think we can understand beauty unless we
can understand what beauty is not and I
should also say that this conversation
the genesis of this conversation comes
from some discussions I've been having
with genre Vicky and Christopher and
master Pietro on my podcast and they've
inspired me to to think about the
subject and also Peter who posted
something from this wonderful Korean
philosopher named Han I can't pronounce
this first part of his name but called
called not reinvented Beauty called
saving Beauty right and so I read this
and this inspired this article which is
why I was invited here so it's
interesting how all of these people have
contributed to this
you know the genesis of this
conversation already and and one of the
things that me and John and Christopher
Kristoff we're talking about was there's
this chorus always right and there's
this chorus of voices you know in our
minds and all around us and you know in
classical theatre you have a chorus and
the chorus is informing you and the
choruses is is creating you know is
coming through you so it's never and
never you like beauty is not an isolated
event it's always it always has a chorus
it always has a course behind it if that
makes any sense so first I want to just
talk about what I what I think beauty is
not and what is the denial of beauty in
our culture and the hijacking of let's
say beauty to be something else
you know entirely so Hagel has this term
called the beautiful soul and he did not
mean that in a flattering sense he meant
that is in a sarcastic sort of insulting
sense he says somebody who's a
beautiful soul is really you know he
meant that this person was was was not
really in touch with some something they
were they were they were faking it they
were putting on a front or a persona or
a moralistic you know interpretation of
beauty so so so they were they were
faking this kind of beauty so that's
that's the beautiful soul
and the beautiful soul is actually a
kind of it's like a kind of uglies and
ugliness because beauty is not just
being pretty or being cute or being nice
or not this facade or the sexiness it's
it also has to have rough rough edges
and one of the things that Hans says in
his essay is he talks about smoothness
how how this culture interprets you know
Beauty as being smooth the smooth right
whereas actual Beauty is a bit rough it
has rough edges I know I would argue
it's not it's not just pretty so it's
it's because there's some gravity
because there's some depth because
there's not only light there's a
contrast of light and darkness there's
not only life there's the meditation of
death you know you can't have beauty
that is divorced from let's say that the
darker others are the the lunar or the
the sadness or the tragic or that kind
of thing you know so so beauty is also
involved in the tragic aspect of life as
well as being the vital and celebratory
aspect to play so I think what's what's
not beauty is is the smooth and I was
thinking the product you know when
something becomes a product it loses for
me its its sense of beauty because
beauty isn't a unique instance it's
something that appears from nothing and
if so I made this little list and on my
list I had beautiful Souls cuteness the
smooth the product and then I had porn
if occation which is a word I learned
from Alexander Bart and I don't mean
just porn you know I mean the porn of
the total poor notification of the
culture
and this means that that you know
everything becomes a sort of porn
everything becomes something to consume
you know as quickly as possible
something that we can just you know
devour so so so you know buy porn I
don't I don't mean you know what sex
workers do I mean as much I mean the
news feeds I mean the social networks I
mean I mean any I mean porn is like
selling what's precious of yourself
tu-tu-tu-tu-tu-tu a big monster you know
like your feelings to to the the social
networks you know and you know
generating cash from that there's
something very ugly about that right I
also wrote ideological possession people
who are possessed by ideology just look
you just look in their faces and they
become there's an ugliness that pervades
them because they're right they know
everything you know they're in
possession of one truth and and
therefore they lose their connection to
reality to beauty and one thing also
that I that I thought is is a denial of
beauty is jargon now we see though you
know a lot of in these communities
there's a lot of jargon pops up a lot of
technical language which people use in a
way that it becomes a sort of in-group
signifier and you know there's there's
there is there is something about
creating language in a community which
is is a form of beauty but then there's
also the attendant jargon I think people
can work you know on language a lot to
make their expressions more powerfully
beautiful I was thinking of game B and I
was thinking that's an ugly term it's
it's a beautiful idea but it's kind of
an ugly term it's it's a placeholder
term so that's just a thought
jargon another thing I wrote was
fragility where people are overly
fragile about everything and they don't
have any flexibility you know
there's a kind of there's a kind of
ugliness to a negative sort of fragility
there's also there's a beautiful kind of
fragility as well which we could also
talk about hubris this is some of my
what is this is the denial of beauty
hubris is a denial of beauty
you know self aggrandizing we're also
self reduction becoming very small
making yourself small all the time it's
it's being tight and small so both those
things control control like I was
thinking of the difference between a
Japanese garden and a Japanese Zen
garden and a let's say I live in France
and in France there's there's much
beauty but there's also this sort of
Imperial architecture which is where you
try to control the landscape everything
has to be under your control and you try
to control and dominate the landscape so
it's this kind of top-down thing right
and in totalitarian societies you see
this you know you see this Imperial
architecture which which is is very you
know it has a power to it but it's a
negative kind of power almost a satanic
power if I could say so and the last
thing I wrote for for the denial of
beauty was noise it just pure pure noise
there's so much noise enos in our minds
not not only outside not only the
ambient sound of a of a city because you
can find a quiet ood even in noise right
Zen master once once told me you know
it's on you you find that the silence in
the noise but just the noisiness of the
culture is a denial you know of beauty
in my estimation
so the next thing so that's my list
which I wrote this morning about what is
a denial of beauty because I think we
need to know what that is before we can
approach what is beauty and actually we
can't define beauty it's I don't believe
that we can define it I don't think we
should define it actually I think we
should consider it a kind of we should
we should approach it with a sense of
serious play this is another one of John
Vicki's terminology so I'm I'm not
trying to define beauty here I'm trying
to give you propositions that you can
play with some of them you know or you
know come from you know my own
reflections and many of them come from
my reflections with with with people
like like like John ever Vecchia and and
Han and Han says Beauty is is is always
has a sense of a veil there's a veil to
beauty right in other words there's
something hidden it's not explicit it's
not all on the surface it's that that
makes it deep right which is the
opposite of the kind of you know porn if
ocation where you have you know wax
bodies with their genitals exposed you
know that's that's not really beauty you
know that's that's probably the
perversion of beauty and again I don't
want to talk you know in moralistic
terms but but the erotic for example it
is when we say the erotic we feel
something very different than we talk
when we talk about porn because because
so what is erotic is is is this dynamic
quality of beauty I think and there's
deeper quality of beauty which is not
explicit always right it eludes us it
tricks us you know it's got a quality of
being a bit of a trickster so I think
that you know I think you know the
denial of beauty is also the denial of
poetry the poche and I don't mean poetry
just written poetry I mean I mean the
poetry a meaning a complex sense of
language and a complex sense of you know
how we communicate with the world and
how the communicates with us and how we
we create you know we have a poetic
manner or way or about a grace about us
which isn't necessarily poetry but but
poetry is is is a it's a primary form of
beauty and that reminds me I was going
to read this at the beginning because I
had a girlfriend when I was in college
and and she had this written on her
mirror in in red ink and it's a quote by
real Kay and it says Beauty is nothing
but the beginning of terror for which we
are barely able to endure and it amazes
us so because it serenely disdains to
destroy us every angel is terrifying
maybe you know that quote I find the
word serenely disdains to destroy us to
be very interesting again and I think
after after after you know reading this
on on my on this person's mirror and I
you know I've been reflecting I
reflected I mean that why is beauty why
is there a terror to beauty and I think
it's something that I'll be thinking
about the rest of my life I don't think
I could I could give you an answer to
any of the questions especially the
question about what is beauty so the
next thing I had written on my thing was
elegance and I think this is related to
stoicism actually so one of the reasons
I think stoicism is very popular in
these days is because it's taking a step
back right from this point if ocation
from this instant gratification from
this you know we've all we've all turned
into you know addicts of some kind and
and stoic stoicism is is is is taking a
step back in and saying we should be
elegant you know in our morality and an
error in our disposition the
next the next part I had was wildness so
if their elegance on one hand and that
and Nietzsche calls out the Apollonian
and then there's the Dionysian and the
Dionysian is this dynamic wildness is
elemental wildness you know so if things
become too stoic become too contained
become too elegant too contrived you
know we have to in a Verve a key
language you have to break the frame you
know and experience some wildness we
have to allow chaos into our lives we
have to you know have a have an orgy
Earth's not not a real ergy but how
about you know well maybe how about
having just some kind of a you know wild
expression you know of the Dionysian you
know which we need to experience that
that's an important experience to have
whatever that means I'm not sure what
that means in this culture and I'm not
sure if we experienced that maybe maybe
you know maybe in this kind of dance
wild dance parties and and whatnot
okay so I also wrote down you know you
know there's something vulnerable about
beauty they're not fragile but
vulnerable right that's a difference so
it's kind of a vulnerability which is
actually a form of strength there's a
complexity right there again i-it's
there's not a simple it's not something
simple it's it's not complicated right
beauty is not complicated we know what
it is we know everybody knows what it is
even though we can't define it because
it's it's complex it's it's a deeply
complex phenomenon beauty and and that's
why again it's it's the it's the compass
maybe in at the same time you're on a
stormy sea and and and and you know you
don't necessarily know which way you're
going so it is the core and it is the
compass but but we have to you have to
sort of keep unveiling these veils that
are presented to us and I guess the last
thing I think I wrote which was contrary
to the idea of noises is there's a
beauty emerges from from from silence at
least in my experience as being somebody
who's done a lot of Buddhist meditation
you know the most the moments where I've
felt the most beauty I have to have been
in moments of intense presence and
silence and that could that could be in
meditation retreat it could be a you
know it could be in a in a relationship
with with a person you know it's but it
but there's always there's always a
ground of silence contained which
contains that expression so um hmm what
else didn't want to say about that I
think I think I've gone through my list
so what if and perhaps could do right
now is just just open you open the
conversation up you know to maybe you
know some you know you know if they're
if what anything I've said has sparked
any have provoked you in any kind of way
or or you think it's true or not true
it's fine we I just want to I just want
to I I love the the first two things
that people said in this conversation
and I thought jeez you know there's
there's so many ways to look at this
it's almost infinite so beauty is the
compass that's that's a good one the
core and and again the fact that as
Timothy says with you know this this
task that we have and the culture is not
responding you know with any kind of
elegance or any kind of beauty to what's
going on it's just increased creasing ly
noisy and that's oh that's the last
thing I want to say it's what we're
doing here is a resistance to that and
so resistance is that's the
revolutionary act of beauty right
it's a resistance to that noise to that
denial of beauty okay yeah thank you
Andrew for these these questions these
ideas provocations I want to remind
everyone that we're gonna do a 30-minute
sense-making around after this so we can
take these questions with us going to
breakout rooms and expand on the
conversation so if you're available love
for you to join us and I do want to
invite your questions or just yeah ideas
anything that you want to bring in
this conversation go ahead put it in the
chat and then I'll just call them people
as it comes up to share and I'm feeling
inspired by this idea like one of the
things I wrote down is I'm rebelling
against these parts of me that are have
been addicted to this immediate
gratification and these facades of
beauty and I appreciate that the way you
ended that Andrew yeah addiction is is
perhaps another denial of beauty right
it's how we deny Beauty because Beauty
can be painful and put us in vulnerable
situations yeah
Timothy would you like to ask you a
question yeah I wondered if for me I was
thinking about what what is beauty for
me and it seems to somehow relate to
authenticity like when either I'm being
deeply authentic or I experience
somebody something a situation that has
that deep authenticity I don't know that
there's any difference between that and
what I perceive as beauty
I wondered what people thought about the
relationship maybe between authenticity
and beauty yeah but an authenticity is
often this is an abused term in some
sense at times because just being
authentic right all the time you know is
what a child does right on some level so
that's the perversion of this idea I
agree with what you're saying you know
what is truly authentic it is beautiful
so I think that that I think we grow
into beauty like there's different
stages of authenticity and I think there
will always have to be beyond ourselves
we can't we can't just be there's
something phony about authenticity if
it's just remaining what it is if it's
not transcending itself does that make
any sense
makes sense to me it reminds me of like
my youngest cousin why my little cousin
why I'm playing with her and she's in
all of her authenticity she doesn't know
that she's being authentic she's being
herself and often times I've put on like
sort of a performance of authenticity
I've noticed that in myself and I can
sort of learn from her that I don't
think she's learned how to do that yet
Jacob would you share your inquiry here
yeah how good is beauty not just in the
dimension of good and if so talk about
beauties is to moralize and if that's
not case why not that's interesting
question and that's what I was talking
to John about that actually and he was
he said wisdom is the virtue of PR
beauty is a virtue of wisdom know what's
that what he said beauty is the virtue
of wisdom yeah yeah I think that's right
and I agree with that statement in a way
and another way I think beauty is beyond
good and evil so I want to put into
Nietzsche inside there because beauty
drives you forward it's like the sirens
in the audience right um it can destroy
your or you know or make you make you I
knew so so there's some there's some
there's some post morality Beauty I
would say that there's an ethical
component always always to to what is
what it's beautiful and I would I would
say ethics in this you know Spinoza
would say ethics is a more dynamic
process than good evil morality does
that make sense we'd have to go long
form to make sense of it I think
but for now sure thank you you're
welcome thank you it's a good question
to carry into the bonus round maybe
great
um I liked that the concept of addiction
got brought up um I see that as one of
the biggest denials of beauty that we
see in our culture and I just wondered
if you could riff a bit about how we
could resist addiction and and get more
beauty in that area of our lives well
that's interesting I was thinking about
my experience during the Kovan you know
crisis and the fact that I didn't have
to go to work and I managed to get
managed to tone down my addiction to
television I stopped watching so much
television and and I think that helped
me perceive the world better so you know
I think I could I could see I could see
things better so so I think that's part
of the you know because there's so much
entertainment we can entertain ourselves
to death right so it's stepping up
that's why stoicism probably is so
important right now because it's
stepping stepping out of that you know
constantly salient and you know
diversion and yeah well I guess
addiction is a contraction it's a self
contraction right you just you wallow in
your inwardness and you stop seeing the
world or you get you get hooked on all
these experiences and you stop seeing
the small things
[Music]
that's perhaps one way to look at it
this huge topic addiction I think again
I'm quoting John for Vicki because I've
spoken to him a lot recently and he
talks about reciprocal narrowing the
world gets narrower and narrower and
narrower the more you know addicted to
you are two things on the other hand
there's a dynamic between our addictions
and and and then wanting to break the
frame right like in the evening I'll
have a glass of wine because my mind is
too contracted and I want to you know I
want to break out of so so you can ride
the edge of your addictions a little bit
and that can be an interesting process
because we all have addictions I mean
we're addicted to coffee
you know we're addicted to everything
that there's a hundred percent addiction
in our culture basically nobody is I
haven't met a person that's not you know
addicted to something
thanks for your question yeah you know
what you asked you a question about
stoicism I probably got stoicism all all
wrong because I'm not an expert but join
the club my friend so thank you paces so
Andrew you previously wrote
stoicism aru's what does it say that
worship is stoicism the religion that is
not a religion I love those juicy
questions so I wonder if you can
elaborate and maybe how that relates to
beauty yeah well perhaps I could speak
from the perspective of you know my own
experience in tradition which is you
know I'm a practitioner of Tanjung
Buddhism and in touch and Buddhism
there's there's you can divide you could
provide Buddhism into if you could
divide it into all kinds of things but
you could divide it into Sutra which is
the path of renunciation which means
giving up things and I kind of think of
that as being a stoic activity at giving
up things like letting go of things and
letting go of all that and then Tantra
means that you you you sorta move into
the area where you you confront energies
directly and and and you kind of maybe
that's the place beyond good and evil
beyond let's say a fixed kind of
morality and I don't mean a morality I
don't mean because you always have you
always have to have a good grounding in
discipline before you can become an
experimental person an experimental
artist and so I think for me the stores
like a pop culture version of stoicism
in a way a very expensive version of
stoicism and a kind of sexy version of
stoicism which I like you know I think
that's great
I don't know how it compares to how
actual stoicism was practiced back in
the day so a rue if it's a ruse it's a
good ruse
does that is that satisfying your your
question Peter or do you want to I
probably couldn't talk to you about this
all day but I think that's good for now
okay Gwen would you share what you
shared in the chat where's Glenn shared
C Segar me he's on the second page
where's Glenn yeah we just got an image
of him in outer space can you hear me
yes perfect so yeah when you were
talking about beauty it reminded me of
something that I heard Jordan Peterson
talked about and he made the point that
you want to surround yourself with
beauty because it is intimidating and it
basically holds up a mirror to all the
things that are ugly right by having the
ultimate form of say beauty in front of
you it makes you self reflect and
realize where you're lacking in the
standard that the artist is presenting
in front of you and I find that the
artists that live right on the edge are
staring dead in the face of beauty and
ugliness and they're able to come back
from that edge and present to the public
at large what they saw and in doing that
when the public interacts with it they
see their own flaws and they see their
own promise for potential and I think
that's the value of having art in your
life and and I didn't realize the full
potential of that until I just took that
wisdom and applied it to my life and
began putting a lot of art into my
immediate space and it is it it makes
you reassess everything that you do in
the presence of something greater than
yourself
and then I happen to see in a
documentary about Jordan Peterson and
how his house is decorated but by sheer
massive pieces of artwork from a lot of
the
or to and and and communist Russia time
period and he basically intimidates
himself with beauty and the ugliness of
beauty at the same time and I just found
that very powerful so thank you for
bringing it up it was a very interesting
topic yeah I like that and and what
comes to mind is the sublime when you
say that and the sublime is always
something you know beyond you and and
it's good it's good it's you know it's
good it's good to always be self trans
transcending and if you if you surround
yourself in beauty yeah yeah there is
there is a sense that the ugliness
because of the world becomes more stark
or evident I agree with that and so so
but so your life becomes you know you
more difficult actually Beauty presents
a difficulty it's not again that's a
it's not a smoothness in the hands in
the Han sense of it it predict it
presents a challenge to you
it's just like you know when you're
rejected in a relationship you know
there's you fall in love with somebody
and then you just crash because you
something and then then you you start to
say okay I have to find out who I am and
I have to you know build myself up from
scratch and and you know I have to meet
that beauty somehow we have to meet it's
something we need to to meet on some
level and and yeah that's why it
serenely disdains to annihilate us yeah
it seems to force you to take the
ultimate responsibility right and and
the more responsibility you take the yes
the more difficult life can seem but
then actually it you kind of transcend
that difficulty through the
responsibility and on the other side
seems to be this this freedom right this
freedom yeah on the other side is the
freedom of play right which is yes my
boundless beauty which doesn't have
reference points
you know there is there's a problem with
the kind of you know so I live in Paris
and sometimes I walk around the louver
and there's these grandiose paintings
and you feel crushed by them because
they're so and then you walk into the
impressionist area and you see Cezanne
and what stays and did is very
interesting you know the painter Paul
Cezanne who invented Impressionism he
was a classically trained painter and he
was trying to do this imposing form of
beauty right he was trying to he
mastered all the the the classical
techniques and then he took all of his
paintings and he put them in a bonfire
and burnt them all cuz he was he knew
that he wasn't really creating beauty he
was creating an imitation right and then
he came up with like you know this these
mountains that have no perspective and
you know and they're just color and and
he started to paint an interior
landscape he started to find his own
sense of beauty which wasn't in a
hierarchical mode right it was it was
beyond that somehow and that that was
this creation of Impressionism and which
doesn't have that hierarchical sense
it's you can look at the mountain of
Sant Victoire from all different angles
and you know and see something it's not
a constricted landscape there's there's
a freedom to it so I I agree with what
Petersen says but that's the first step
I would say that's the suit trionic step
if I can use Buddhist terminology or the
stoic stoic step yeah you remind me of
kind of like what Carl Jung or junior
tolking did like talking said that he
entered into the land of fairy and he he
gave you the stories that he saw and it
seems that Jung entered the land of the
unconsciousness right and he he brought
back the stories so to your point yeah
there seems to be something beyond that
that hierarchy that people want to fight
in right it seems to be like this
dominant culture ideal that you have to
fight to be on the top but it almost
seems when you enter into this other
liminal space that there is no more
competition it seems to be
Hey what are your what are you seeing
from your perspective and let's share
stories and see if we witness the same
thing or not for Vickie said that that
beauty is the sweet spot between
suchness and more nests and more nests
is this expensive quality right you you
know you go beyond yourself you just you
know it's too much right it's it's
unbearable right in a sense and and and
it just keeps going and going and going
and going right and then the suchness is
the most intimate the most near the most
domestic the most it's that's on the
earth it's grounded and and so so we're
always going you know we always have to
experiment with more earnest right and
then and then come down to such nacelle
ever dynamic process you know then we we
can we can become connected with
something that we might be able to call
beauty you show you a question sorry
Brendan sorry was you wanted to finish
what he was saying so you want to just
continue oh sure I was gonna say I mean
there's a very good point that you kind
of have to reach out into chaos while
you still keep one foot grounded and
sometimes you can fall 100% in the chaos
and the ones that seem to come back seem
to be the the wounded people that heal
themselves and they throw out times have
been called shamans and I think we need
to see more and more of that kind of
archaic revival to take terence
mckenna's idea and and respect the the
archaic traditions that allowed human
beings to reach the point where we're at
right now I mean I think diving into
that that space that you're talking
about introduces a lot of people to what
the ancients saw and that we are now
trying to rediscover and recreate thank
you for letting me finish
Thank You Glenn David I think this is a
good time for your question and thoughts
on transcendence yeah you said notice
like my heart's pounding and there's
like all this aliveness in me and like
all my nervous how am I excited like I
really care about this and listening to
you Andrew when you're like kind of
gesturing towards beauty like we can't
really define it you can kind of point
towards it I kept thinking of
transcendence or like the sacred like
beauty maybe is like getting a glimpse
of the transcendence and then definitely
our culture seems to kind of obliterate
the sacred through abstraction and you
know commodification and all these
things and and so I'm curious in your
world what is the relationship between
beauty and transcendence or the sacred
like what's the difference yeah that's I
had an interesting again I'm thinking of
my conversation with for Vicki about
this and he said the sacred and I was
thinking of Renny Gerard you know who is
he had this theory about the sacred the
sacred is is is is often related to
violence in some kind of a way so
there's there's two kinds of sacred
there's you know there's there's there's
what is what is hidden there's this
hidden hidden aspect of the sacred and
and then I I said John what I think it's
it's not the sacred I think it's way you
have to worship right that that that's a
more direct relationship to what is
divine is is to worship because if
there's something sacred then you have a
distance from it a little bit you're
making its sacred you're making it
precious you're you're not really very
yet on the other hand he's and then he
said we a but it's like a fire you need
to be sort of you need to have a
distance from the fire so so that's an
interesting discussion in terms of
transcendence there's these two
movements there's transcendence and then
there's the imminence so it's like
breathing breathing in and breathing out
we
you know Trent you're always you're you
always need should be on the edge right
so there's an edge to beauty right so
that you're transcending yourself all
the time
yeah but but but but you should you
should also be bringing that down to the
most domestic the most ordinary the most
real you know making it real so so
beauty has to be grounded in the real
that's why all this phantasmagorical
images of beauty aren't necessarily
butyl beauty 'fl that's why the smooth
isn't necessarily beautiful or the
pornographic because it hasn't been it
hasn't been brought into I could say the
heart and on some level if I can be
prosaic about it and there's this
there's this movie I don't know you know
the movie metropolis and they talk about
like the head and the hands need to join
in the heart
so there's beauty is a meeting place
maybe it's funny how this this subject
is so vast and infinite you could just
find different angles of it you know
there's no end to it to to the important
you know to the importance of meditating
on on the beautiful I think and you
don't come up with platonic ideals this
is of let's say symmetry or something is
beautiful or asymmetry is beautiful or
you know whatever theory you have a
beauty is this kind of ends up to be
bullshit no because it's it's beyond
propositional knowing
Lisa if you'd like maybe expand on your
question about relationships yeah thank
you you Tyson I think what Andrew just
said about the meeting place that's what
God I got wondering about the if is
Beauty to goodness analogous to the
moment of that meeting place the
encounter in that meeting place versus
any kind of critique of judgment or
agency I'm fascinated by this question
about the distinction between truth and
beauty and I'm thinking about a lot
about time in this conversation so the
relationship to the relationship that we
can only encounter in the moment you
know well a few thoughts when you are
speaking the truth and beauty are not
separate things right yeah you know you
know and often we associate truth with
with the masculine and beauty with the
feminine but and we have both those
things inside of us right and they're
not separate that's one thought thought
I had when you're speaking and in terms
of time I say that beauty is oh it's
it's completely unseats
I think I have a French word on my head
on say said it can't be seized it can't
be captured it can't be it can't be
reduced to anything it's always related
to the relationship and in the moment in
time as you say I think I think it's
it's very much related to context and
and this living moment in time and
Heidegger talked about dies n being
being in time the beingness quality of
time and it's it's only alive and it
only lives because
it's going to reach its end so there's a
poignant quality to that right it's it's
maybe Gray's comment reminds me of one
of the questions that I woke up with
this morning which was something like
why beauty and why this conversation now
as I've been sort of I feel like forced
to look at in in a good way but forced
to look at a lot of the suffering and
the pain in the world that maybe before
I was maybe a little naive too or
ignoring or distracted from it's become
more in my face and so I was questioning
myself and like is this a sign of my
privilege if I get to have a
conversation about beauty and kind of
going down these these thoughts but then
having these reminders come in about why
this conversation and deepening this
relationship is important to me right
now and so maybe I appreciate you asking
this question I'd love for you to share
it so so basically why is Beauty
important right now like as as we're as
we have a sense that the world is sort
of falling apart and I would say that
there's a temptation to live in this
kind of space of propositional you know
idea law ideological thinking but it but
it ends up being very counterproductive
often you know you just waste a lot of
time thinking about you know and
watching the news and and and so so I I
do think that beauty has a revolutionary
aspect but I don't think it's
propositional and and I don't think we
should deny it for any kind of social
program any kind of movement any kind of
ideology I don't I don't think we should
deny it because it is a compass eye that
was I think that was those Timothy who
said that at the beginning it is it is a
compass and if we don't have that come
we're lost you know maybe would you like
to expand on that at all I respond I
like your name maybe I think I think
maybe is a good name because cuz it's
cuz it's this we don't know right we
don't know what it is that's perfect
yeah anytime anybody qualifies their
certainty I'm like what is that does
that mean I think the only thing I would
ask as like a follow-up is um how does
it feel brave to you to prioritize
beauty does it ever feel hard is there
anything you ever have to do to like
psych yourself up to be like no Beauty
matters
I don't throw what the haters well it's
because we have in our minds you know
weird ideas of beauty it's always
related to the cosmetic or the aesthetic
or the cultural but I think I think I
think courage is inherited in beauty and
all these perennial notions like
theythey we were talking about indras
net right Enders net is like everything
is reflected in everything else so
virtue is reflected in beauty which is
reflected in courage which is reflected
in wisdom which is reflected in you know
they're all reef they're all they're all
part of the you know they're all part of
this dynamic process and you know and
it's it's a living textured experience
and well I think maybe even politics
could have an aspect of beautiful the
beauty if it was done right it almost
never is alright and we can see that
well you know what they call game a it's
it's just it's it when it when when
something becomes reified and and it's
just it's it's it's a dead land it's
like
it's a land of the dead right so so yeah
I think any you wouldn't want I wouldn't
want to limit beauty or poetry it's to
any particular domain I think it
politics okay you know it's not my thing
so much but other people I know are more
involved in politics and you know
philosophy you know whatever you do if
you're a waitress you know now you could
do that with with a certain kind of
beauty you know if you if you're you
know it's also related to a kind of
style as well you know somehow and you
can feel it when you're in the presence
of that somehow there's a coherence to
it that's Jordan halls term but there's
also a mystery so it's not just
coherence it's not just oh you know
clarity right it's also mystery and
depth and the shadowy you know dimension
thank you Andrew are there any questions
or inquiries thoughts final thoughts
ideas that you might want to leave us
with as we go into breakout rooms and
continue this conversation
yeah like any any question or inquiry
that is for you at the edge of your
thinking now where we stand now or just
anything you might want to leave us with
to consider and dialogue around okay
Paul I didn't see you there no I just
seen you know
don't hear me when I ask that question
Paul was gonna challenge my notion of
beauty but I'm also open to us I like
being challenged to challenge is good
antagonism can be you know there's a
positive kind of antagonism there's a
positive kind of fight
I don't want Beauty to be just soft and
sweet and nice and you know I learned
that a lot from from my podcast partner
Alexander bard he he likes to get into
fights but he does it in a way where
that's very respectful of other people
at the same time so
is that your real name may be great cuz
gray is great to a great I like that I
like the color gray gray is not usually
considered to be a beautiful color but
you know Paris is gray is good because
it's neither black nor white it's just
in between colors this liminal color you
don't often think of graves being a
beautiful color we think of it as being
kind of depressing but there's there's
millions of different shades of gray
right to quote a famous movie but you
know there's violet grey and green grey
and red grey grey and grey can can
reflect so many different things so so
there's much beauty in grey it's pouring
rain outside now it's grey stormy skies
I love it Peter before we do begin our
next 30-minute session and you got to
bounce
do you have any closing words or
invitations or maybe even questions that
you would like us as the stoah to take
into this sense-making session okay
that's a good question first Andrew
thank you my friends working with the
store today and thank you for our sexy
and beautiful emcee of the evening Tyson
Wagner for you know launch of this new
series with us yeah I do have a question
that I could leave everyone off with but
I'll plug a few announcements or events
invitations as Tyson put it so we have a
wisdom gym here at the store and we have
two events coming up today relational
exegesis with Jessica that's every
Thursday at 4 p.m. Eastern Time and we
basically read a text together so we
build a relationship with the text while
rebuilding community Oz with each other
that's been pretty fun and then we have
a shame breakthrough boot camp with our
shame educator AJ bond that's at 6 p.m.
Eastern time and he takes us through all
these different exercises and I highly
recommend that then we have a couple of
like really cool wild sessions
Brent Cooper that meta modern
troublemaker is is coming in to doing a
session called who's sensing the sense
makers this Friday at 5:30 p.m. Eastern
Time and uses
we're gonna criticize all of us and then
we can criticize them back and I think
we have James fucking cars for author of
finite infinite games he's having a
session playing they have been a game
during a meta crisis that's June 17th I
think this is a Wednesday at 3 p.m.
Eastern Time so definitely check out all
that and the question I will leave the
one that I'm wondering about and you can
wonder about too is how do we make the
stove the most beautiful place possible
or digital campfires like the stove that
things that take pison back in thank you
Peter
by quick show of hands who's going to
stay the next 30 minutes for breakout
rooms okay good well thank you so much
Andrew for being here and bringing this
conversation to the stoah I look forward
to continuing it and maybe as things
evolve and unfold and we all continue
this conversation we can have you back
another time in the future and you're
always welcome here around the campfire
for any session I really appreciate you
being here thank you thanks so much that
was a lot of fun all right so anybody
that has to go now you may do so and
then for the rest of you I will start
organizing breakout rooms in a minute or
two so if you want to take a quick break
or anything feel free to do so